Chi Sigma Theta Sorority; Records ua806
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Chi Sigma Theta Sorority Records1914-2014, Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Chi Sigma Theta Sorority
ua806
15.58 cubic ft.
The Chi Sigma Theta Sorority Records contain documents related to the history, activities and alumnae of the Chi Sigma Theta Sorority at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of select files noted below. Researchers seeking access to these materials should contact the head of Special Collections and Archives.
Acquisition Information
A small portion of these records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by the Alumni Association in 1991. The bulk of the records were deposited by Carol Siver, Class of 1965, in 2002. Since then the collection has been augmented several times through donations from individual alumni, including at the 100th anniversary celebration in June 2014.
Biographical Sketch
Chi Sigma Theta, a local sorority founded at the New York State College for Teachers (now the University at Albany), traced its origins to the Newman Club, a campus Catholic study society founded in 1908. The Newman Club reorganized to form Kappa Nu Sorority on October 5, 1914. In 1920 the name of the sorority was changed to Chi Sigma Theta for reasons that are unclear. The Sorority had one main objective: "Chi Sigma Theta established its ideals of loyalty, companionship, and sincerity, which each girl takes a pledge to uphold" (State College News, November 13, 1964, 5).
Like many sororities, Chi Sigma Theta maintained several traditions over the course of its history. Some of these included hosting holiday parties, faculty teas, formal dinners, building Homecoming floats, a candlelight ceremony for members who became engaged, and of course organizing the yearly rush and pledge period. These activities are extensively documented in the scrapbooks kept by the official sorority historian each year.
In the mid-1960s Greek societies at the State University of New York at Albany were forced to sell their houses and move to dormitories on the new Uptown Campus. Maintaining a Greek society in the dormitories was contingent on retaining sufficient members to justify setting aside the floor and rooms. In the 1970s Chi Sigma Theta, along with other local Greek societies at the University, suffered a steady decline in membership. The active chapter of Chi Sigma Theta dissolved in 1980.
The sorority did not accept this setback as permanent. With the help of a robust alumnae association, Chi Sigma Theta was reactivated on campus as a local sorority in the Spring of 1986 with the initiation of seven new members.
The attempt to reestablish Chi Sigma Theta as a local sorority failed. In 1988, the remaining members of the active chapter merged with the University at Albany chapter of Phi Sigma Sigma, a national sorority. As of at least 2013 Phi Sigma Sigma is no longer an active sorority on the Albany campus. However, Chi Sigma Theta still enjoys an active alumnae association.
Scope and Contents
The Chi Sigma Theta Sorority Records include administrative records such as constitutions, member lists, and meeting minutes; subject files related to sorority activities and traditions such as event publicity and songs; and several years' worth of composite photographs of the sorority members. There are many scrapbooks kept by the sorority historian, documenting Chi Sigma Theta's activities each year, as well as a box of preservation photocopies of these scrapbooks. The memorabilia includes textiles such as blazers, blankets and banners; jewelry such as rings, pins and necklaces; and various other items bearing the Chi Sigma symbol.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 and 3 are arranged alphabetically. Series 2 is arranged chronologically.
Greek letter societies--New York (State)--Albany; Sorority songs; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Women--New York (State)--Albany--Societies and clubs; Correspondence; Newsletters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; UAlbany Student Groups; Minutes (administrative records); State University of New York at Albany; Chi Sigma Theta Sorority
- Administrative and Subject Files, 1914-1989; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records relating to the administration and activities of the Chi Sigma Theta Sorority. Meeting minutes, membership and initiation lists, constitutions, pledge books and other materials document the sorority's actitivites. Although there are some older materials, the bulk of this series documents the 1960s through the 1980s. This series also includes sorority traditions, publicity materials, and some records relating to alumnae. Please note that while the collection contains composite photographs of all sorority members across several decades, the dates are not inclusive.
  - Alumnae Association minutes, 1946-1950; 1955-1956; 1958-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Alumnae News, The Chi Sigma Theta Press and News from Chi Sigma Theta, 1975; 1982-1987; 2014 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Alumni Association board members list, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Alumni Reunion reception, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Composite photographs, 1956-1988 (Oversized 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Composite photographs, 1966; 1972-1973; 1977-1978 (Flat-file 1)
  - Conflict Party bid, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Constitution, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Constitution, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Constitution, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Constitution, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Constitution, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Contents of 1986 pledge binder - Laura, 1985-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Contents of 1986 pledge binder - Robin (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1968; 1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Dissolution and merger correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Event publicity, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Event publicity, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Event publicity, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Event publicity, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Event publicity, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Expression, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Family tree of Joan Bostwick '52, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Formation of Kappa Nu The Echo, 1914 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Guest book, 1966-1969 (Oversized 2)
  - Guest book - [RESTRICTED], 1974-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 23)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Guest book - [RESTRICTED], 1974-1978 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Initiation pledge lists photocopies, ca. 1916-1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Invitatin to join Chi Sigma Theta, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - List of officers, 1921-1945; 1951-1962 (Oversized 2)
  - Meeting rules, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Membership lists, ca. 1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1971-1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes and membership list, ca. 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - 100th Anniversary Reunion, 2014 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Panhellenic Rush, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Photographs (preservation photocopies), 1981 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Pledge book, ca. 1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Pledge books, ca. 1956; ca. 1960 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Pledge books, 1974; 1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Pledge list, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Pledge songs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Reformation correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Rush poster, 1985 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - 75th Anniversary Luncheon, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Signatures of pledge class members, 1920-1986 (Oversized 2)
  - Songs, ca. 1970s (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Sorority faculty list, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Special Group Housing correspondence and agreements, 1977-1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - State College News (bound volume), 1957 February-1957 December (Oversized 2)
  - Treasurer's report, 1962 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 18)
- Scrapbooks, 1952-1987; 2
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series consists mostly of scrapbooks kept by Chi Sigma Theta's official sorority historian, documenting the activities of the sorority for that year. There are also two scrapbooks kept by individual sorority members.
  - Scrapbook, 1952-1956 (Oversized 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1955-1959 (Oversized 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Oversized 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Oversized 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1960 (Oversized 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1962-1963 (Oversized 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1965 (Oversized 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1965-1966 (Oversized 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1967 (Oversized 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1967-1968 (Oversized 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1968-1969 (Oversized 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1969-1970 (Oversized 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1970-1971 (Oversized 15)
  - Scrapbook, 1971 Fall (Oversized 16)
  - Scrapbook, 1972 Spring (Oversized 17)
  - Scrapbook, 1973-1974 (Oversized 18)
  - Scrapbook, 1973 Spring (Oversized 19)
  - Scrapbook, 1973 Fall (Oversized 20-21)
  - Pledge Scrapbook, with 1974 composite photograph included, 1974 Fall (Oversized 27)
  - Scrapbook, 1974 Spring (Oversized 22-23)
  - Scrapbook, 1976 Spring (Oversized 24)
  - Scrapbook, 1986-1987 (Oversized 25)
  - Scrapbook, 1987 (Oversized 26)
- Memorabilia, 1960-2014; Undated; 3
  This series contains objects related to the Chi Sigma Theta Sorority. It includes jewelry, textiles such as blazers and banners, household items like plates and silverware, Spring Weekend keepsakes, and various other objects related to Chi Sigma.
  Some of the pins in this collection were passed on to active sorority members from alumnae. Further information on the custodial history of those items may be found in the Chi Sigma Theta collection file.
  - Ashtray, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Banner, red and white, 3' x 4', Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Banner, red and white, 4' x 6', ca. 1986 (Artifact-box 2)
  - Beer mug, 1966 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Blanket, red and white, 4.5' x 3.5', Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Blanket, purple, 2' x 28", Undated (Artifact-box 2)
  - Blankets, red and white, 4.5' x 3.5', Undated (Artifact-box 10)
  - Blazer, red, Undated (Artifact-box 4)
  - Blazer, cream, Undated (Artifact-box 4)
  - Blazer, cream, Undated (Artifact-box 4)
  - Burlap wall hanging, Undated (Artifact-box 4)
  - Chi Sigma Theta golf shirt, red, Undated (Artifact-box 4)
  - Chi Sigma Theta mug with "Allison" brand, 1977 (Artifact-box 8)
  - Chi Sigma Theta mug with "Marietta" brand, 1964 (Artifact-box 8)
  - Glassware, Undated (Artifact-box 12)
  - Leather Chi Sigma Theta shield, framed, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Leather Chi Sigma Theta shield, unframed, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Leather pillow cases (2), Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Leather sign, Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Necklaces, gold tone, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Necklaces, silver tone, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - 100th anniversary beads, 2014 (Artifact-box 9)
  - 100th anniversary poster, 2014 (Flat-file 2)
  - Outstanding Juniors plaque, 1966-1973 (Artifact-box 7)
  - Paper and ribbon crowns, red and white, Undated (Artifact-box 9)
  - Pillow labeled Chi Sigma Theta and "Allison", Undated (Artifact-box 5)
  - Pins, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Pin belonging to Ruth Lockard Hanford '27, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Pin possibly belonging to Catherine M. Hagel '17, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Pin with torch, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Plate, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Ring, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Ring, pin and pendant, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Rush Party Invitation, ca. 1960 (Box 3 (3-Memorabilia), Folder 1)
  - Silverware, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - Spring Rush '88 button, 1988 (Artifact-box 6)
  - Spring Weekend jug, 1965 (Artifact-box 3)
  - Spring Weekend jugs, 1965; 3 jugs. (Artifact-box 11)
  - Spring Weekend beer stein, 1966 (Artifact-box 6)
  - Spring Weekend program, 1960 (Box 3 (3-Memorabilia), Folder 2)
  - Spring Weekend towel, 1967 (Artifact-box 2)
  - Stamp, etched copper plate, Undated (Artifact-box 6)
  - State University of New York at Albany mug, Undated (Artifact-box 8)
  - Sweatshirt, Undated (Artifact-box 4)